Boker tov, happy Lag BaOmer, happy Mother’s Day. We pick up on
Daf Kuf Yud Gimmel. We are about eight lines in with a
little Alef in a half circle—in half parenthesis it says Siman Amar.
So there’s a question what this word Siman means. Some speak because
it’s not normally Siman indicates that we’re going to have some mnemonic,
but we don’t have a mnemonic here. The Mesoras HaShas says yesh
lomar shehu shem Amora, because you know reading it, Siman says, Rava
bar bar Shila says. So, or Rava, so anyway but I don’t
know what else to do with that word. But anyway, what we’re
up to is we’re still, you know, the Gemara was still a
whole discussion about how do you know that a husband inherits from
his wife? So the classic drasha is
uvenasatem es nachalaso lish’eiro hakarov eilav, to his flesh, and reading that
the flesh means his wife.
And of course the problem is that the grammar’s all wrong. It
should mean that it goes to his wife rather than he gets
from his wife. So that led to all these other psukim, a
whole debate of Rebbi Akiva and Rebbi Yishmael, and particularly Rebbi Yishmael
saying that the psukim that say do not let the nachala, when
it’s speaking about the Bnos Tzelafchad, which the Gemara’s later going to
say was limited to that generation, don’t let them marry from another
tribe so that the inheritance does not, velo sishov nachala, the inheritance
does not
get turned away from, taken away from one tribe to another tribe.
So how would it go from one tribe to another tribe if
they married out? Obviously it means when the woman dies or if
she gets an inheritance, it passes on to a different tribe. So
that would either be her son, because her son goes by her
husband, her husband’s tribe, or her husband. So we already established that
when a woman dies it goes to her son. Can we learn
from those psukim that they’re also referring to a case that when
a woman dies it goes to her husband or not? Maybe they’re
all talking about it going to her son. And that would be
the question whether those psukim are evidence that a husband inherits from
his wife. And that’s what the Gemara said to grapple with yesterday.
How clear is it that they could be talking about husband, maybe
they’re all talking about son. Now the Gemara picks up here today
with showing that again going back to those psukim and showing two
Braisas that once—that both seem to read one about the son and
one about the husband. So maybe actually we’ll double back a little
bit and read from there, okay, and we’ll pick up from the
bottom of Kuf Yud Beis Amud Beis where it says—bottom there’s almost
no Kuf Yud Beis anyway. So the Gemara says like this,
it says like this, actually you’re right, it’s the whole Kuf Yud
Beis Amud Beis. All right, fine, whatever, but to go quickly. Three
lines from the top of Kuf Yud Beis Amud Beis: Tanya besibas
haben vesanya besibas habaal. We turned one Braisa that the way the
Rashbam reads it starts with the idea of the nachala going through
the son and going away from the mother’s tribe and the other
by turning through the baal, the husband away from the mother’s tribe,
but essentially the Braisas say the same thing. I’ll tell you in
a minute how Tosafos reads the Braisas. Tanya besibas haben velo sishov
nachala livnei Yisrael mimatteh el matteh. Do not let it turn from
one tribe to another. Besibas haben haksav midaber. That means don’t marry
a man from outside your tribe, speaking to the Bnos Tzelafchad, and
then it’ll go pass through the son away from the tribe, away
from the mother’s tribe. At omer besibas haben, so it shows that
a son inherits from his mother. At omer besibas haben haksav midaber,
you say it’s referring to the turning away that happens through the
son, o eino ela besibas habaal, maybe it’s the turning that comes
from the baal, from the husband, the husband inherits his wife? Keshu
omer velo sishov nachala mimatteh el matteh achair, almost an identical pasuk,
harei besibas habaal amur. That shows you that it’s talking about the
husband inheriting. Ha mani mikayaim velo sishov nachala livnei Yisrael mimatteh el
matteh? Besibas haben. So there’s two psukim that are almost identical. So
the one el matteh achair is talking about the husband. So the
one that says mimatteh el matteh must mean that it also can
go away from the mother’s tribe, from the woman’s tribe by going
through her son. So the Gemara’s going to ask
that, okay. Tanya idach, we talk about the Braisa. Now you’ll note
the other way the—this girsa that we have in our Gemara, the
Rashbam’s girsa, it’s mamash the exact same. The same pasuk is read
about the husband and the same pasuk is read about the son.
It’s just a question which pasuk the Braisa starts with. Velo sishov
nachala mimatteh el matteh achair, the word achair is the pasuk about
the husband. Besibas habaal haksav midaber. That’s if you check that’s exactly
what the previous Braisa said, except this one starts with the pasuk
about the husband and then includes the pasuk about the son. At
omer besibas habaal o eino ela besibas haben, you say that’s about
the husband, maybe it’s referring to the son? Keshu omer velo sishov
nachala livnei Yisrael mimatteh el matteh harei haseibas haben amura.
So when it says the other pasuk, don’t go from one tribe
to another, you see that it talks about the passing away from
the tribe that can happen through the son. Ha mani mikayaim—the Gemara’s
going to ask, miko—ha mani mikayaim velo sishov nachala mimatteh el matteh
achair? Besibas habaal haksav midaber. It’s talking about going through the husband.
So again according— to the רשב"ם Rashbam these are the exact same
ברייתא, braisa, they just start with a different order. So it's bizarre
a little bit. תוספות Tosafos says that the גמרא Gemara says one
is talking about the husband and one is talking about the son,
since according to them they're both talking about both and the only
question is which and they're even linking it to the same פסוק.
pasuk. The only question is which what do you call it, which
you know which פסוק pasuk the ברייתא braisa starts with. So תוספות's
Tosafos גירסא girsa is different. תוספות's Tosafos גירסא girsa is because we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara
that the פסוק, pasuk,
okay, ולא תסוב נחלה ממטה למטה
אחר—the velo tisov nachala mimateh lemateh acher word אחר acher is a
way to know it because according to one of the דרשות drashos
that's going to be the focus, I think the מסקנא maskana that's
going to be the focus—that's about the בעל. baal. Okay,
both ברייתות braisos agree with that. So the פסוק pasuk is what
do you do with the פסוק, pasuk, the other פסוק? pasuk? ולא
תסוב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה למטה. velo tisov nachala livnei Yisrael mimateh
lemateh. Oh, that could be but that's the בנים. banim.
No, the אחר acher is the בעל. baal. No, no, the בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael is the thing. Oh, that could be, but that's
not what, that's not ולא תסוב נחלה ממטה למטה אחר. velo tisov
nachala mimateh lemateh acher. It could be, you could be, but the
גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. You're right, it is, according to this
ברייתא, braisa, the גמרא Gemara doesn't link it to the word בן.
ben. I hear your point, I hear your point, but the גמרא
Gemara doesn't say that. But it doesn't matter, this is I'm going
to just say the way תוספות Tosafos says it. Okay, according to
both the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it, this is about the
בעל baal and this is about the בן. ben. Okay, Micah makes
an interesting point, maybe the בן ben is based on the בן
ben here, that's a nice point. Okay, that's the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it and the only difference of the ברייתות braisos is
which order they're presented in. תוספות Tosafos says then you wouldn't say
that one of them is about the בעל baal and one is
about the בן ben since they both say the exact same thing,
they're just presenting them in different orders. So תוספות Tosafos says no,
that the ברייתא braisa the גמרא Gemara says that is about the
בעל baal actually reads that both of them are about the בעל.
baal. He has a different גירסא girsa in the גמרא Gemara that
it says ולא תסוב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה למטה, velo tisov nachala
livnei Yisrael mimateh lemateh, בנחלת הבעל הכתוב אומר. benachalas habaal hakasuv omer.
Maybe it means בנחלת הבן? benachalas haben? So it says no, this
says בעל, baal, so once this says בעל baal this must mean
בעל baal as well. That one ברייתא braisa says they're both בעל
baal and the other ברייתא braisa says this is בעל baal and
this is בן. ben. So according to תוספות Tosafos at least it
explains how there's some debate in the ברייתות. braisos. They all agree
this one is the בעל baal and the question is this one,
some say it means the בן, ben, once this is בעל baal
this is the בן, ben, then they know if this is the
בעל baal this is also the בעל. baal. Okay, so I don't
know, but anyway, but that's at least the way that תוספות Tosafos
has it. So you know like the גמרא Gemara said earlier, to
be שני לאוין. shenei lavin. Okay, the Rebbe said it before about
the בן, ben, now we're saying it about the בעל. baal. Anyway,
bottom line, what תוספות Tosafos makes nicer, and this explains where the
גמרא Gemara continues—A, it makes nicer why there's some debate between the
ברייתות, braisos, but why it also makes it nicer is that the
גמרא's Gemara going to focus on why is it clear that this
is talking about the בעל. baal. From the way the רשב"ם Rashbam
is saying it, we could have just as easily of said why
is it clear that this is talking about the בן ben and
we could have given Micah's wonderful answer that it says בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. But the גמרא's Gemara going to focus on that everybody
agrees this one is talking about the בעל, baal, how do we
know this פסוק pasuk is talking about the בעל? baal? So let's
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, דכולי עלמא מיהא, d'kulei alma miha, ממטה למטה אחר, mimateh lemateh
acher, בהסיבת הבעל הכתוב מדבר. behaseivas habaal hakasuv medaber.
Everybody agrees this פסוק pasuk is talking about don't let it pass
to the husband. Now again, that's only for that generation, that בנות
צלפחד bnos Tzelofchad were not allowed to marry husbands from another tribe
so it wouldn't pass either to the בן ben or to the
husband of a different tribe. But this פסוק pasuk means don't pass
to the husband. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי משמע? mai mashma?
Where do you see that that means passing to the husband? Maybe
it means passing to the בן? ben? So the גמרא Gemara says
סימנא, simana, I don't know what to do with the word סימנא,
simana, אמר רבה בר רב שילא, Amar Rabba bar Rav Shila, אמר
קרא, amar kra, איש. ish. Okay,
so it says כי איש, ki ish, בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, what's
the end of the פסוק pasuk Micah? כי איש בנחלתו ינחלו בני
ישראל ידבקו בני ישראל, ki ish benachalato yinchalu Bnei Yisrael yidbeku Bnei
Yisrael, thank you. כי איש בנחלתו ידבקו מטות
בני ישראל. ki ish benachalato yidbeku matos Bnei Yisrael. So since it
says כי איש, ki ish, we're talking about that the passing that
happens to a man, but not only to a man, to a
husband, איש ish like איש נעמי, ish Naomi, the רשב"ם Rashbam quotes
the פסוק. pasuk. So even though that's not פשט pshat of the
פסוק, pasuk, the word איש ish signals we're focusing on a husband.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, Micah's going to
ask what the גמרא's Gemara about to ask. The גמרא Gemara says
תרווייהו איש כתיב בהו. tarveihu ish kesiv behu. The other פסוק pasuk
says איש. ish.
What's the end of the other פסוק pasuk Micah? ולא תסוב נחלה
לבני ישראל ממטה למטה אל מטה, velo tisov nachala livnei Yisrael mimateh
lemateh el mateh, that's it אל
מטה, el mateh, yeah,
כי איש, ki ish, בנחלת מטה אבותיו, benachalas mateh avosav, ידבקו בני
ישראל. yidbeku Bnei Yisrael. Yeah, they're almost identical פסוקים, psukim, ידבקו בני
ישראל. yidbeku Bnei Yisrael. So the גמרא Gemara says you can't say
איש ish signals husband because this also says איש. ish. One minute
let's finish reading it, okay? אלא אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר קרא ידבקו. ela amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar kra yidbeku. Shows husband because why do you think? ודבק
באשתו. Veyidbak be'ishto.
So the גמרא Gemara says, "One minute. So תרוייהו וידבקו כתיבו, travaiyu
veyidbeku ketivu, this also says וידבקו." Veyidbeku.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רבא אמר קרא וידבקו
מטות. Ella amar Rava amar kra Veyidbeku matot. So somehow here it
says the word
מטות. matot. So very few differences. One difference is that this says
מטות matot and this says מטה. mateh. So how does מטות matot
mean? It's still not clear to me how, apparently the way the
רשב"ם—it's Rashbam not clear to me why מטות matot signals husband, but
I think what it's saying is through the דביקה deveika you connect,
there are two tribes. Okay? So וידבקו מטות. Veyidbeku matot. The woman
is דבק באשתו, daveik be'ishto, right, and, or דבק באשה, daveik be'isha,
thank you.
And now you have two tribes are co-joined, so it emphasizes that
the husband is a different tribe. Okay? This is not the וידבקו
Veyidbeku it's like the בני ישראל. bnei Yisrael. Maybe again, very nice
what Michal said, it works here too. It's the connecting to the
son. Okay? So the son. Anyway, but here it's the co-joining of
two tribes, that's the דרשה. drasha. מטות matot versus מטה. mateh. The
focus on the husband. I want to read a little more, then
you can ask. Okay? אלא, Ella, so the גמרא Gemara says, where
were we? אמר קרא מטות. Amar kra matot. רב אשי אמר אמר
קרא ממטה למטה אחר ובין לאב אחר הוא. Rav Ashi amar amar
kra mimmateh lemateh acher uvein le'av acher hu. That pits
this word אחר acher is one word that is not in the
other פסוק. pasuk. And that means that the person who it's passing
to is to some degree an other. Like we talk nowadays about
othering, okay? So a child is always going to be biologically related
to you. But a husband, at the end of the day, there
is no biological connection. There could be death, there could be divorce,
you know, at a certain point and then the connection is severed.
So although there is a דביקה, deveika, they come together, to some
degree the husband is always an other in the way the child
is not. So the words here "other" or the word here מטות
matot signal that the passing is going to be to a husband,
whereas this will either according to תוספות Tosafot could also be a
husband because this is, or this could be a son. Okay? So
these are in the end the two words that might signal it.
Now, one—two other points and then we'll ask Michal's question. So one
is, what was the גמרא Gemara thinking when it said the word
איש ish or וידבקו? Veyidbeku? Didn't it know that איש ish or
וידבקו Veyidbeku here as well? So look at a little תוספות Tosafot
here is going to shock you. תוספות Tosafot says תרוייהו נמי וידבקו
כתיב בהו, travaiyu nami veyidbeku ketiv behu, פעמים שלא היו בקיאין בפסוקים.
pe'amim shelo hayu beki'in bipesukim. Okay,
which is like "whoa", like I mean this straightforward פסוקים, pesukim, like
it's not even in נ"ך, Nach, you know, it's in תורה. Torah.
וכן מצינו בסוף שורש נגח את הפרה, vechen matzinu besof shoresh nagach
et hapara, מפני מה לא נאמר בדברות הראשונות
טוב. mipnei ma lo ne'emar bedibrot harishonot tov. So one,
I think I forget, a תנא tanna asked another, or an אמורה,
amora, "Why does it not say in the second דברות dibrot טוב?"
tov? אמר ליה עד שאתה שואלני שאיני יודע אם נאמר בהם טוב
אם לאו. amar leh ad she'atta sho'aleni she'eini yode'a im ne'emar bahem
tov im lav. "What do you mean do I—like I don't know
if one says טוב tov and the other doesn't say טוב, tov,
don't ask me that question," okay? Anyway, so that's—so תוספות Tosafot says
maybe they just mamesh didn't know the other פסוק. pasuk. But then
he doesn't like it. He says ומיהו הכא תימא דמכי דייקי תרוייהו
איש כתיב בהו, umihu hacha teima demachi dayaiki travaiyu ish ketiv behu,
משמע דידעי פסוקי mashma deyade'i pesukei and so forth.
From the continuation of the גמרא Gemara it doesn't sound like they
really didn't know. It sounds like they knew and somehow it wasn't
bothering them. So the רשב"ם Rashbam explains that the sort of reason
of the גמרא, Gemara, what does it mean that they were saying
this says וידבקו, Veyidbeku, this also says וידבקו, Veyidbeku, this is, this
also says איש? ish? The רשב"ם Rashbam was just saying that let
me remind myself exactly how the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it,
one minute. One minute.
So if you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, he says like this,
the second medium-sized line. רשב"ם Rashbam says the following. ומיהו גם המתרץ
היה יודע דבהאי קרא וידבקו כתיב, umihu gam hametaretz haya yode'a dehe'hai
kra veyidbeku ketiv, דבכל קרי בי רב הוא, devichol kari bei rav
hu, just go ask in the חדר, cheder, go ask the little
kids, they'll tell you what the פסוקים pesukim say. ואמאי דבעינן לעיל
ממי משמע דהאי קרא ממטה למטה אחר בסיבות הבעל מיירי, ve'amai deba'inan
le'eil mimmai mashma dehai kra mimmateh lemateh acher besibat habaal mairi, אתא
איהו למימר דשפיר משמע בסיבות הבעל מיירי דכתיב ביה איש, ata ihu
lemeimar deshapir mashma besibat habaal mairi dechtiv bei ish, ותמה עצמך למה
גם הראשון אינו מדבר בסיבות הבעל כיוון דכתיב ביה איש, vethima atzmecha
lama gam harishon eino medaber besibat habaal keivan dechtiv bei ish, אלא
משום דמוקמינן ליה בסיבות
הבן. ella mishum demokminan leh besibat haben. Okay,
so basically the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says is we know that
both say איש. ish. All the גמרא Gemara was saying was, was
that איש ish was a sufficient reason to say it was talking
about the husband. And once we said it could—it was talking about
the husband, didn't mean this one wasn't talking about the husband. It
meant this one was talking about the husband. So once this one
was talking about the husband, we're not saying in contrast to this.
We were just saying the word איש ish and the word וידבקו
Veyidbeku signaled that it was talking. But then the גמרא Gemara says,
and once this was talking about the husband, this is already going
to talk about something else. So we didn't say that this one
wasn't at those words, we just said because it had those words,
we could state that it was talking about the husband. This one
also had the words, but once this one was, this one by
necessity has to be talking about something else. And then the גמרא
Gemara said back, "But I don't get it." Then it still doesn't
explain why you started here and said this was talking about something
else. You might as well just start here and say this was
talking about something else. But anyway, the רשב"ם Rashbam makes the גמרא
Gemara a little better 'cause the claim never was why is this
husband in contrast to this. Then it never would have said. It
said איש ish because it knew it said איש ish here. It
just meant what signaled that this was husband? We gave a word
and then we said but then just as easily, but you know,
but you might just as easily have started by the other פסוק.
pasuk. So in the end we had to come up with a
word that was only here that explained why we started with this
פסוק pasuk and then we let this one mean something else. I'm
just looking at the flow of the פסוקים. pesukim. Yeah. This is
my conclusion, which is opposite to the גמרא, Gemara, but this is
at least the way I'm looking at it. It talks הטוב בעיניהם
תהיינה לנשים, ha-tov b'eineihem tihyena l'nashim, right? Then the next פסוק pasuk
ולא תסב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה אל מטה. v'lo tisov nachala livnei
Yisrael mimateh el mateh. So that means it's the husband 'cause that's
talking about getting married, right? So that to me, that's the בעל.
baal. Then it talks about וכל בת יורשת נחלה, v'chol bat yoreshet
nachala, then ולא תסב נחלה ממטה אל מטה אחר. v'lo tisov nachala
mimateh el mateh acher. Because who's יורש? yoresh? Children are generally יורש.
yoresh. So over here, the יורש... yoresh... Okay. So the first one
is talking about the husband. I hear. All right, maybe. I don't
know what to tell you. Maybe. The thing with בני ישראל... Bnei
Yisrael... I didn't think I made it up, like פשט pshat from
the ילקוט שמעוני Yalkut Shimoni in the bottom? Yeah, it just says
ולא תסב נחלה לבני ישראל ממטה אל מטה. v'lo tisov nachala livnei
Yisrael mimateh el mateh. That's הבן. habein. Right. I'm just saying the
גמרא Gemara does not make the connection to the בן ben and
the word בני. Bnei. But I think it's an excellent point. Here
it also says
בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, doesn't it? ידבקו מטות בני ישראל. yidbeku matot
Bnei Yisrael. No, because here it just says בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
earlier on. It says בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael earlier on here. Yeah.
Okay. All right, let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay.
אמר רבי ינאי אמר רבי ומטו בה משמיה דרבי יהושע בן קרחה.
Amar Rabbi Yannai amar Rabbi u-mattu bah mishmeih de-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha.
Says Rabbi Yannai in the name of Rabbi and they inclined towards
it in the name of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, which is an
interesting phrase. Maybe it means it wasn't like a direct tradition but
somehow, anyway, an inferred tradition.
מניין לבעל שאינו נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק. Minayin l'baal she'eino notel b'rauy k'vemuchzak.
Here's a very interesting הלכה. halacha. How do you know the husband
does not get things that were ראוי? rauy? ראוי rauy means things
that were fit to come to his wife in the equal way
that he gets מוחזק, muchzak, things that his wife already owns. Like
a בכור. bechor. It's the same issue of a בכור bechor getting
פי שנים, pi shenayim, correct? Okay. And here's the idea. Here's the
man.
Okay. Here's the man. Here's his wife. All right. And here's the
wife's father. Okay. Now here, and I don't know, and here's the
wife's son or daughter. Okay. So,
wife, let's say the husband... the father dies, the wife inherits, he...
the father only has daughters, okay? And then the wife dies, the
husband gets, right? That's what would happen in that case, right? If
it had had that order. One, first he died and then she
died. We could use another color. Okay. Let's say, however, the order
was different. Let's say first she died. That was number one. And
then he died. And that was number two. So what would happen?
She died, then her father died. The grandfather. He only had daughters.
Who do you think is going to inherit that? His... well, was
there any other daughter? No, it's her only daughter. So then it
goes back down to the... to the...
what, he's the daughter's... He only has daughters. Who died first? Who
died first? She died first. That's why I have a one there.
She died first. She. She.
So then her father... it goes back to the father, no? No,
the father... wait, it not goes back. He has no property. He's
the one with the property. Right. And then he dies. Where does
that property go? Does she have a son? She does. Okay.
So you say it goes to the son. Right. So you are
correct. You are correct. It does go to the son because the
idea is that... the idea is that, forget this more case of
more complicated, let's just have a simple case here. Here's a guy.
Okay. He's got a brother, he's got a father, okay, and he's
got a child. Okay. He dies.
His child is... has died. His child has a child. Okay. What
happens? Right? Remember, first son, then father, then brother. That's normally the
order. One, two, three. You remember that from what we've been doing
until now? Okay. He dies, his son is dead, does it go
to the father or does it go to his... his son's son?
Son's son. Son's son. The idea is that you keep on going,
any descendant takes the place of the parent. Not only that, just...
just to reiterate, I think I've said this before, but to reiterate
it, let's say his son has a daughter.
Okay. And that's male or whatever. Okay. It would go to his
granddaughter before his father or his brother. Any descendant, okay, comes prior,
right, to the... going the next sort of level. Okay. So, you
got that, right? So in this case, ignore the husband. Okay, this
guy died, his daughter isn't around, before you go to some other
direction, you're going to go to any descendant of the daughter. It's
going to go to his grandson. That is correct. The only question
though is that, why don't we say that it goes to the
husband? Because what happens when a woman dies? What happens when a
woman dies? He remarries. What happens when a woman dies with property
and there's a son? Who gets it? Her husband or son?
The husband. Husband. The husband gets it. Okay, the husband comes first.
So if when the woman dies and there's property the husband gets
before the son, so why don't you say when the grandfather dies
and the woman isn't around, why doesn't the property flow that way?
Because that would happen if the woman... That would... so if she
had it, property she had is called מוחזק. muchzak. Property she had
when she dies goes to her husband before her son. Is that
צאן ברזל Tzon Barzel or something? No, no, it just means that
she's already in possession of it. Yeah, I mean whatever it would
be,
it would
be what do you call it? It would be probably נכסי מלוג,
nichsei milog, but I don't want to get into that. It just
means she's in possession. So anything she's in possession when she dies
goes to her husband. But when she dies, she is not in
possession of this piece of property. That's ראוי. ra'uy. That she was
in line to inherit it, but she had not yet inherited it
when she died. So that's called ראוי. ra'uy. So the husband does
not get in the ראוי ra'uy the way he would get in
the מוחזק. muchzak. Things that were in her possession when she died
the husband gets. Things that she was in line to get when
she died, husband doesn't get, and that does not go in the
same path, that goes down. Okay? Who owned that ראוי? ra'uy? The
grandfather. She is in line to get it, so the stuff that's
מוחזק muchzak the husband gets, the stuff she's in line to get
and then she dies and then only after she dies it comes
down, that goes to her son. If she deceased her father? Yes.
Now you understand the logic for this. I think the logic makes
a lot of sense. Exactly. Thank you very much. After she's dead,
this child is still related to her and still related to the
grandfather. The husband is no longer related to her once she's dead.
I mean you know the biological connection to this family has severed.
The connection was through marriage and the marriage no longer exists. Okay?
So this guy, why should he give it to his son-in-law? His
son-in-law isn't related to him. Think about it that way. Who's related
to him? His grandson. When she dies at the moment of death
she still like married to the husband, so anything she has when
she dies goes to her husband. But after she's dead, that stuff
does not go to this guy's son-in-law, that stuff is going to
go to his grandchild. So for the purposes of נחלה nachala once
she dies they're not related? Yeah. Sorry, David. There's a problem with
the logic. I mean using the words as if she's still married
then she's either dead or she's not. Well, okay, that's we look
at it like at the moment of death, right, not after death.
After death they're not married. But you're right. I mean it's a
little like, yeah, exactly. But for the purposes of נחלה nachala once
she dies they're not related. For the purposes of אבילות aveilus once
she dies they are. Well, it all just defines by the moment
of death. I understand. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, so מנא
לן לבעל שאינו נוטל בראוי Mina lan l'ba'al she'eino notel b'ra'uy he
doesn't get the stuff that his wife was in line to receive
כבמוחזק k'vemuchzak the same way he gets stuff that his wife was
already in possession of? שנאמר Shene'emar the verse says ושגוב הוליד את
יאיר ויהי לו עשרים ושלש ערים v'Seguv holid et Ya'ir v'hayu lo
esrim v'shalosh arim same thing we did before בארץ הגלעד. b'eretz haGil'ad.
מנא ליה ליאיר שלא היה לו לשגוב Mina lei l'Ya'ir shelo hayah
lo l'Seguv where did יאיר Ya'ir have property that his father didn't
have? Last time we said that he got it through his wife
and his wife died. Okay, but now we're going to say a
different version of it. אלא מלמד שנשא שגוב אשה ומתה בחיי מורישיה
Ella melamed shenasa Seguv ishah umetah bechayei morishe'ha he married a woman
and she and
his and his I'm sorry, I mean before we said יאיר Ya'ir
married a woman and he inherited from his wife, שגוב Seguv is
the father. Now we're going to say יאיר Ya'ir didn't get it
from his wife, יאיר Ya'ir got it
right? Here's יאיר Ya'ir and שגוב. Seguv. So יאיר Ya'ir has property
that שגוב Seguv did not have. So last time the גמרא Gemara
said his wife brought in the property, okay, and that's how he
had property that שגוב Seguv did not have. Now we're going to
say that no, it was יאיר's Ya'ir mother who had it, but
it was really his grandfather that had it. Okay, so how did
יאיר Ya'ir get property that שגוב Seguv did not have? Because his
mother first died and then his grandfather died and then it went
straight down to him. And did not go to שגוב Seguv his
father.
All right? So אלא מלמד שנשא שגוב Seguv אשה ומתה בחיי מורישיה
Ella melamed shenasa Seguv ishah umetah bechayei morishe'ha
she died in the life of her bequeathers.
and וזה אומר ve-ze omer and similarly ואלעזר בן אהרן
מת ויקברו אותו ve-Elazar ben Aharon met vayikberu oto same story. פנחס
Pinchas had this property that he buried his father אהרן Aharon in.
מנא ליה לפנחס Mina lei le-Pinchas that he buried... that he buried
אלעזר Elazar in? מנא ליה לפנחס שלא היה לו לאלעזר Mina lei
le-Pinchas she-lo haya lo le-Elazar מלמד melamed same story שנשא אלעזר אשה
shenasa Elazar isha
that אלעזר Elazar married a woman, פנחס's Pinchas mother, ומתה בחיי מורישיה,
umeta bechaye morisheha,
she died when her bequeathers were still alive, ומתו מורישיה umetu morisheha
her bequeathers died, וירשה פנחס veyirshah Pinchas and then they passed down
straight to פנחס Pinchas the grandson and אלעזר Elazar did not get
it. ומאי וזה אומר Ummai ve-ze omer why do you need the
פסוק pasuk same thing like we said before, וכי תימא יאיר דהוה
נסיב איתתא ומתה וירית לה vechi teima Yair dahava nasiv iteta umeta
veyarit lah like we said before,
maybe יאיר Yair got it directly through his wife? His wife brought
in property, not through his mother. תלמוד לומר ואלעזר בן אהרן מת.
Talmud lomar ve-Elazar ben Aharon met. וכי תימא דנפלה ליה בשדה חרמים
vechi teima denafela lei bisdeh charamim and so the extra פסוק pasuk
must be telling you it's a different circumstance again. Maybe just telling
you the story, but okay. וכי תימא דנפלה ליה בשדה חרמים vechi
teima denafela lei bisdeh charamim like the גמרא Gemara said before, maybe
פנחס Pinchas got it because it was some type of a dedicated
field to הקדש hekdesh and it wasn't passing through a wife or
through a or through a grandson. אמר קרא בנו בנו. Amar kara
bno bno.
It says פנחס בנו, Pinchas bno, his son. So why did it
have to say the words בנו? bno? We know פנחס Pinchas was
אלעזר's Elazar son. נחלה הראויה לו וירשה בנו. Nachala harauya lo veyirshah
bno. Just want to say in this case here it says פנחס
בנו, Pinchas bno, okay, so this was אלעזר Elazar and פנחס, Pinchas,
that this was his son, it was property that he might have
expected to be entitled to, but בנו bno is like in contrast
to him. He didn't get it, rather his son got it. So
because it was property that came through his wife, so you could
have thought that he maybe should have been entitled but no, he
didn't get it, it went to his son. Anyway, they're learning this
principle that it goes straight to the grandson, it doesn't go to
him once she's already dead, which makes sense. But now I want
to read an important תוספות Tosafos because תוספות Tosafos says, well then
why don't we learn from this a general principle that maybe how
do we know, or let me rephrase the question, how do we
know when a woman dies her husband comes before her son? We've
learned from a פסוק pasuk that her husband inherits, we learned from
a פסוק pasuk her son inherits, the two ways the נחלה nachala
goes to a different מטה. matteh. How do we know husband comes
before son, especially since once she's dead it goes straight to the
grandson? Once she's dead, then maybe even if she has property and
she dies, maybe her goes to her son, the one who's biologically
connected to her, prior to going to her husband? How do we
know that? How do we know that the order is husband first
and then son? So look at תוספות. Tosafos. מתה בחיי מורישיה דהוי
ירשה יאיר. meta bechaye morisheha dehavi yarshah Yair.
ואם תאמר דבן יורש בראוי נכסי אמו ובעל אינו יורש מנלן דבעל
קודם לבן? Ve-im tomar d-ben yoresh beraui nichsei imo u-baal eino yoresh
menalan de-baal kodem le-ben? Since a son gets stuff that was coming
to his mother and the husband does not, so their son at
least in this way comes before the mother in general, how do
you know that when a woman has property, she her husband inherits
her before her son? ויש לומר כיון שהבעל אינו יורש מחמת קורבא
אלא מחמת שאירות, Ve-yesh lomar keivan she-habaal eino yoresh machamat kurva ela
machamat sheerut, which is interesting, right, לשארו? li-she'ero? So לשארו li-she'ero as
I've been telling you according to the רשב"א Rashba according to רמב"ן
Ramban means flesh, והיו לבשר אחד. ve-hayu le-vasar echad. So it's a
type of a flesh, but it's almost like a flesh that is
that is not through through a biological connection. So תוספות Tosafos contrasts
that flesh of husband and wife to קורבא, kurva, to biologically
related, שהם חשובים כבשר אחד. she-hem chashuvim ke-vasar echad. תוספות Tosafos says
as also flesh, right, והיו לבשר אחד, ve-hayu le-vasar echad, okay, but
it's not the same as a biological connection. אם כן כמו שהוא
קודם לשאר קרובים כך הוא קודם לבן דמה לי האי ומה לי
האי. im ken kemo she-hu kodem li-shear krovim kach hu kodem le-ben
de-mah li hai u-mah li hai. תוספות Tosafos says look, it's gonna
go, forget the grandfather here, you have wife and son, so our
question is does it go first to husband or does it go
first to son? Okay, that's our question, which way does it go?
And תוספות Tosafos says but what we know for sure is, let's
say there's no husband and no son, where's the woman's property gonna
go? Back up to her father, so it'll go to her father
or it'll go or it'll go to her sibling, okay, right? So
it'll go to somebody who's biologically related to her. If there was
no husband and no son, right, it'll go to a somebody who's
a relative, okay, father, father, father, brother, etc. So תוספות Tosafos says
ah, but we say it's clear, it's clear that it's gonna be
that only if there's no father no husband and no son. So
תוספות Tosafos says, ignoring the son for a moment, what you see
is her relationship to her husband is stronger than her biological relationship
for purposes of inheritance to her father or a brother, right, cause
there's no
question. than the biological relationship to father or brother because it'll go
first to her husband before any of these. Once we've established this
aspect of בשר אחד basar echad trumps this biological relationship then we're
going to say it's also going to trump this biological relationship. That
the בשר אחד basar echad means that this is like ממש mamash
one and that happens before you start looking at relatives. So the
oneness of husband and wife comes before any relatives. So the same
way this oneness comes before these relatives it comes before this relative.
But when there's no husband then it'll go to the son. Also
assuming son without that. Right that's what Michael said. Right that is
true. Although of course you could have a son without a husband
but you know you need a father. Right just a question of
what's that connection of son. Right correct correct. Okay so it's very
interesting. The husband comes before the son. This idea I like the
phrase in תוספות Tosafot there's שאירות she'erut and בשר אחד basar echad
which is not the same as קורבה korvah right what I'm calling
biological relation. This comes first but nevertheless once she's already dead and
then property is passing down then this relationship doesn't exist anymore and
then it's going to go to the son and not to the
husband. Okay. Yeah there's something to the fact that יאיר Yair happens
to be from this extended צלפחד. Tzelophehad.
Oh
that's an interesting point I hadn't thought about that. Maybe there is.
Or maybe they say like maybe that's why they're going to those
פסוקים pesukim or whatever. Yeah that's a good point. Since she's one
of the aunts. Right right right yeah yeah it's a good point.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues. There is a way by
the way that this guy can get this property of course God
forbid if his son dies right? His this man's grandson inherited and
then if the grandson were to predecease and the father was still
alive right it would go back it would go up to the
father that way. Property that she didn't have already before when she
was
alive. She
dies this
then he dies this property passes down to his grandson okay? If
his grandson were to die while the father was still alive the
father would inherit from his son if there were no siblings. And
what if the son died before the grandfather died? And so he
had no descendant? Yeah then it would go well assuming then it
would go to his father or his brother. But can we just
say that the relationship with the husband was stronger than the... That's
what I'm saying but not after she's dead. After she's dead that
relationship doesn't exist anymore. That's why he does not get from that
property okay? If the property happens after she's dead there's no relationship
anymore.
If she has property when she dies it goes to her husband
but if property comes to her through her after she's dead then
there's no relationship. But didn't you say when the son died what
where was the status already? No she was already dead though. She
was already dead. But he's related to the son he's not related
to his wife anymore. Okay so we'll go up to the father.
Or do it the other way the grandson dies yeah then the
grandfather right so she inherits... She's alive? She's alive. Yeah so of
course she inherits from her father and then it goes to her
husband even if the son's alive. Yeah. All right ובני אחות. uvenei
achot. Now
sons of sisters which means... I'm confused what's the whole thing? No
I know you're right. It's an excellent point. It's an excellent point.
Okay no no no okay okay.
So here's a sister here's a sister's child okay so this guy
dies and then it can pass to... Wait who is... I'm just...
Whatever there's a man I don't know ראובן Reuven דינה Dinah I
don't know what we'll call him Steve. You know they're already one
first generation in America they're already getting American. Okay anyway okay so
it passes so assuming let's say that דינה Dinah is not alive
okay and he dies so it passes so he dies. He doesn't
have any children okay? First it would go to children right? Who's
Steve? Steve is דינה's Dinah son. His nephew you're saying. דינה's Dinah
son yeah. Okay this is his nephew right? This is his nephew.
He dies. Okay first it would go to his children. He doesn't
have any children okay. Then it would go to his father. His
father is dead. Then it would go to his siblings. His only
living sibling is his sister דינה. Dinah. Okay all right his sister
not his wife right I'm sorry. Okay יעקב Yaakov I'm sorry okay.
All right so דינה Dinah and ראובן Reuven are siblings. Right I
know that's why I took those names. Okay so people enough enough.
Okay anyway all right so then no children then it would go...
יעקב *Yaakov* is dead, so it goes to siblings, first brothers, no
brothers, so then it goes to דינה *Dina*. דינה *Dina*'s not alive.
So then it goes to דינה *Dina*'s surviving children. Okay, so we're
going... so that's how if it would go from an uncle to
a nephew.
All right, בני אחות *Bnei Achot*. Right. תנא בני אחות ולא בנות
אחות *Tana Bnei Achot velo Bnot Achot*. Now that would only be
to... it would only go to Steve, it wouldn't go to, I
don't know, Sharon. Okay. Now, does that really... why not? I thought
that we'd go... I thought we'd go to all surviving children. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, למאי הלכתא *L'mai hilchsa*? What do you
mean it won't go to a niece, it'll only go to a
nephew? אמר רב ששת *Amar Rav Sheshet*, right,
לקדם *likadem*. No, no, no. It just means like we've seen elsewhere
again, it was that the son will come before the... the man
will come before the woman, the son will come before the daughter.
So if Steve is... if there's no male children, Sharon will inherit.
Or if Steve didn't have any children... or Steve's... right, that's correct
too. Okay, the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* seems to get that wrong. תוספות
Tosefos *Tosafot* says the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* was... made a mistake, he
wasn't... anyway, but, yes. First it would go to male children, then
male children's descendants. If there were no male children's descendants and there
was nothing in this line, right then it would go to Sharon.
If Sharon inherited it and Steve died, Steve didn't have any descendants,
Sharon would finally get it. Right. Now you do remember there was
a discussion when property came through a mother, right, which it's sort
of... it's doing here, right, then they might divide equally, but this
is assuming not. This is assuming no matter where the property is
coming from or whatever, you know, at the same level, the boys
come before the girls. And correct, if Steve had children, they would
take his place and they would come before Sharon, but if there's
no line here, then Sharon would get it. Yes. Okay, yeah. So
all these... all these סוגיות *sugyot*... I am now all of a
sudden thinking... it's like lockstep. Like this is what happens. Right. So
there's no possibility like in contemporary like American society, like you go
to a lawyer and you decide in your will... sure you are,
that's going to be the next פרק perek *perek*. This sets up
the inheritance of the תורה Torah *Torah*, and then the remainder of
the מסכת *masechet* is about writing wills. So I can ignore all
this if I wanted to? If you made a will. Right. And
it's going to be about the rabbinic institution of wills. Okay, well
thought I would just... thank you for mentioning. Okay, good. Preparing us
for what's coming later. I'm always looking ahead. Right. But this is
the line of inheritance if a person dies intestate. Do you like
that word? Okay, right. Anyway. All right. So, intestate means without a
will. I understand. אמר רב ששת לקדם *Amar Rav Sheshet likadem*. תני
רב שמואל בר רב יצחק קמיה דרב הונא *Tanei Rav Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak kamei deRav Huna* וירש
*veyarash*... so it says, the פסוק *pasuk* says, right... והעברתם את נחלתו
לבתו *vehe'evartem et nachalato lebito*. Right... the... yeah, the whole thing, right,
it says ואם אין לו בן *v'im ein lo ben*, it says,
you know, ואיש כי ימות ובן אין לו *v'ish ki yamut uben
ein lo*, ובן אין לו *uben ein lo*, והעברתם *vehe'evartem*, והעברתם נחלתו
*vehe'evartem nachalato*, נחלתו לבתו *nachalato lebito*. ואם אין לו בת *Ve'im
ein lo bat*, ונתתם את נחלתו לאחיו *u'netattem et nachalato l'echav*. ואם
אין אחים לאביו *Ve'im ein achim l'aviv*, אחים לאביו *achim l'aviv*, ונתתם
את נחלתו לשארו הקרוב אליו *u'netattem et nachalato lish'ero hakaroov eilav*, הקרוב
אליו *hakaroov eilav*, וירש אותה *veyarash
otah*. וירש אותה *Veyarash otah*. So the דרשה *drasha* is like this:
all of these ו *vavs*, ו *vavs*, ו *vavs*, they're all connected,
okay, וירש אותה *veyarash otah*, and it basically says you inherit it,
so let's see what the דרשה *drasha* is, okay, וירש אותה *veyarash
otah*. וירש מקיש *Veyarash
makish*, I'm going to say, מקיש ירושה yerusha שניה לירושה ראשונה *makish
yerusha shniya liyerusha rishona*. It links the second inheritance to the first
inheritance. מה ירושה ראשונה yerusha rishona בן קודם לבת אף ירושה yerusha.
שניה בן קודם לבת *Mah yerusha rishona ben kodem l'bat, af yerusha
shniya ben kodem l'bat*. So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* reads
it is, the same way all of these are the different lines
of inheritance: son, daughter, brother, uncle... so the same way up here,
son comes before daughter, at any level that you're going to be
in the chart of inheritance, son is going to come before daughter.
Okay. So that's basically how we know that even though this is
going through the sister and then down, we're going to retain the
idea of son before daughter. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: what were we...
and תוספות Tosefos *Tosafot* says that we mean that even if you
keep on going down generations, that like the ירושה שניה *yerusha shniya*,
right, is like so let's say it's even something not in the
פסוקים psukim, *psukim*, right, Steve dies, and Steve has a son and
a daughter. Okay. No matter how many generations you go down, if
there's... if we're at the same level, the sons are going to
come before the daughters. Like so ירושה שניה *yerusha shniya* is relevant...
What's
the רשב"ם Rashbam says ירושה ראשונה yerusha rishona, is sons, and ירושה
שנייה yerusha shniya is anybody that's after the children in their, in
these things as well, their sons will come before their daughters. תוספות
Tosafot says it's really just like any level down, even things that
are not in the פסוקים, okay, that even like a second generation,
not only is the first generation sons before daughters, right, meaning we
could be talking even the guy himself dies, forget all of this,
right, this is ירושה ראשונה, the guy's sons come before his daughter,
and then ירושה שנייה yerusha shniya is the guy's son is dead,
and he has a son and a daughter, and his, the grandson
will come before the granddaughter. So it's not, the רשב"ם Rashbam, says
ירושה שנייה yerusha shniya are going these different
levels, תוספות Tosafot ירושה שנייה yerusha shniya is just going down generations.
But either way it's saying the point, sons wherever you are on
the chart, son is going to come before daughter. Okay, but a
granddaughter, a grand, yeah whatever it is, a granddaughter here
can come before a daughter, right, because it's, he's representing, right, this,
you know, ultimately representing the father here. Okay. Yes? Is that understood?
If, if Steve is dead and he left behind a daughter, his
grand, his daughter will get it before his sister. Before his sister,
yeah. All right. Right, and similarly, when would the sister ever get?
If there's no kids. What? No
children. It'd have to be no children for the sister to get.
If Steve had no children. Right. And then Sharon would get it
from Steve if Steve died. Yeah, exactly. Or, right, so Steve could
have a great, great, great, great granddaughter that'll come before his sister.
And that would make Sharon very frustrated. Exactly. Or his brothers also.
What? He would, the great, great, great granddaughter would come before, not
before his brother, if there were two brothers then this brother would
get half and this great, great, great granddaughter would get half.
If there were two brothers and a sister, Steve, Fred, and Sharon.
Fred gets half, Steve gets half, Steve isn't alive so the half
passes down. Okay. And then also the same way, like if Steve
is a, you know, if there's a brother and a sister over
there and that brother had
many kids, God knows how far, like that'd be before that other,
before the sister. Right. If he had, if he had a son
and a daughter and that son had way down here a surviving
great-granddaughter, it would go all the way, it would... Right. And that'd
come before that other. Exactly. Yeah.
All right.
Okay, okay, תני רבה בר חיננא אחוהי דרב נחמן: Tanei Rabba bar
Chinnana achohi d'Rav Nachman: והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו, V'haya b'yom hanchilo
et banav, okay, but now we're going, finally we're shifting gears to
away from all of these charts of inheritance and talking about some
other principles of
ירושה about, about judging cases of
ירושה. והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו, V'haya b'yom hanchilo et banav, it'll
be on the day that he bequeaths to his children. ביום אתה
מפיל נחלות, B'yom atah mapil nachalot, in the day is when you
distribute inheritances, ואי אתה מפיל נחלות בלילה, v'ee atah mapil nachalot balayla,
and you don't distribute it at night. That's the same thing as
the... אמר ליה אביי, Ama lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said: אלא מעתה
דשכיב ביממא הוא דירתי ליה בני? Ela meita d'shachib biyomama hu d'yarsi
lei bnei? What are you saying? If somebody dies in the day,
his sons inherit from him? ודשכיב בלילה לא ירתי ליה בני? V'dah
d'shachib balayla lo yarsi lei bnei? And if he dies at night,
they don't? דפסוק והיה ביום הנחילו את בניו de pasuk V'haya b'yom
hanchilo et banav means the guy died and the property passed down,
so what, you have to die during the daytime? So the גמרא
Gemara. says: דילמא דין נחלות קמשמע לן. Dilma din nachalot kamashma lan.
Maybe you meant the adjudication of נחלה. nachala. דתניא, Detanya, what can
I tell you, so you see there, you've got to be precise.
דתניא: Detanya: והיתה לבני ישראל לחקת משפט. V'hayata livnei Yisrael lechukat mishpat.
This shall be for בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael for an edict of
judgment. This is at the end of the case
of the בנות צלפחד. Bnot Tzelafchad. Okay, so what, anything? Yeah.
הוקרה כל הפרשה כולה להיות דין. Hukra kol haparsha kulla leyot din.
So because it's calling it a חוקה, chuka, it all has a
status of a דין. din. Now what does it mean it has
the status of a דין? din? So רשב"ם Rashbam says two things,
what we're going to see in a minute issue of בית דין,
beit din, but the רשב"ם Rashbam, says first of all directly this
issue of יום: yom: דיני ממונות dinei mamonot are anything that's a
דין, din, it
has to be judged in the day. דיני נפשות dinei nefashot start
in the day and have to end in the day. Any adjudication
of דיני ממונות dinei mamonot starts in the day but could end
at night. Okay, so when we say ביום אתה beyom atah we're
saying it's a דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. Any adjudication of a question
of inheritance has to start in the day, it could end at
night but has to start in the day. Now saying it that
way is just saying that it's דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, it's that
lower category. So what else would I have thought it would be?
Of course, it's a, it's a monetary dispute, of course it's דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot. So the רשב"ם Rashbam, says, well, maybe I would
have thought it was like you know two partners who were just
dividing up their partnership and maybe it wasn't even a דין din
question, maybe it was more like a בירור, birur, we're just clarifying
who gets which, it's not really a case of a litigant
and
a defendant, so... Who is the closest surviving relative, then you could
say that's not really a דין. din. That's really just let's just
do a let's just research it. Let's just find out who's the
closest let's just do a genealogical chart we'll find out who the
closest that's not a דין. din. It becomes a דין din when
it's like okay we know there are these three sons and now
they're fighting about who gets which portion of the estate. Okay? So
for the רשב"ם, Rashbam the חידוש chidush is that we don't say
it's just a trivial fact finding thing, it's דין din and it
has to be like any other דיני ממונות dinei mammonos begin in
the daytime. I do want to say though the חוקת משפט chukat
mishpat for some ראשונים rishonim is important that it says that נחלה
nachala is weightier than דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. For example, a major,
major issue the ראשונים rishonim were asked about was can we forget
about this entire פרק and just go by the secular laws of
inheritance. Why should we be able to go by the secular laws
of inheritance? דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchuta dina. Okay? So the same
way by monetary issues we can go by secular laws, by inheritance
it's a monetary question let's go by secular laws. So רמב"ם Rambam
already says no. He says this is חוקת משפט כתיב בה. chukat
mishpat kesiv bei. It's a חוק. chok. You can it's not like
a normal question of a transaction between two people, which you could
understand, any transaction between two people ultimately it's about the implicit contract
between us and that could be shaped by the laws of the
country we live in. But this the person's dead and the תורה
Torah dictates who gets it next. So that's not a question of
a normal דיני ממונות dinei mammonos and it's not ruled by דינא
דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchuta dina. So the reason I point that out
is that the חוקת משפט chukat mishpat here is just used to
say it's like normal דיני ממונות, dinei mammonos, it starts in the
day. But other ראשונים rishonim use the חוק chok word to say
it's weightier than דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. Okay so that's one thing
we're saying that it starts in the day. Okay? אורעו דכל הפרשה
כולה להוות דין. ura d'chol haparsha kula l'havot din. Okay? For for
the הלכה halacha that it starts in the day. And now the
גמרא Gemara is going to say another הלכה halacha that is based
on it. But you know what? I'm going to stop here because
the other one gets more confusing. But I do want to say
another point that תוספות Tosafot makes about אורעו להוות דין. ura l'havot
din. תוספות Tosafot says it's relatively obvious that it would require a
בית דין Beis Din and it would require a יום yom for
the reasons we said. תוספות Tosafot says the חידוש chidush is that
he says let's say somebody is dying and we're going to see
this case coming tomorrow, he's dying, he distributes his property on his
deathbed. There are three people there that are witnessing it. Okay? And
and they de facto become a בית דין. Beis Din. So then
one of the brothers though says I don't want them to judge
this case. I don't trust these three guys. I want to go
to a different בית דין. Beis Din. So he says so תוספות
Tosafot says no, it is a דין din in the sense that
if there's a בית דין Beis Din present they can impose the
דין din on the people that were there. Obviously if there's no
בית דין Beis Din present, you know, a relative died, we're debating
who gets what, what did he exactly distribute in his will or
so on, then we have to figure out a venue that everybody
agrees upon, right, like any other case you've got to get a
venue that both like the litigant and defendant and how do you
pick a venue. But because of the דין din idea and this
is similar to the ideas about the חוק, chok, it's not just
an agreement between parties. There's something that the תורה is imposing this.
תוספות Tosafot says if there was a בית דין Beis Din present
at the moment of death you cannot choose another בית דין. Beis
Din. They can force their rule on the people that were present.
Alright, so that's sort of the take תוספות Tosafot has, but the
רשב"ם Rashbam I think is the more simple read of the גמרא.
He says number one it's a דין din that it requires to
begin by יום yom and tomorrow we'll look about other ways in
which this is considered to be a דין. din. Okay? Yes. Did
you say that a criminal or
a capital case has to be judged in or has to be
in the daytime? Is that what you said? Yes. Every case has
to start in the daytime. Civil law can end at night. Criminal
law has to end in the day. The judgment has to be
in the day. So for the רשב"ם, the חידוש chidush number one
is this actually requires a בית דין Beis Din and it's really
a דין din and it's not just some simple trivial division. תוספות
says that's obvious. Of course it's דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. The bigger
חידוש chidush is that the בית דין Beis Din can enforce it
on people and they don't get to choose their בית דין Beis
Din if the בית דין Beis Din was present. So the inheritance
question then is in the category of has to be by day?
דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. No, it's not like criminal. It's like civil.
It has to start in the day.
Oh, so but because your last example was saying this is different
from... That's why that's my point. My point is according to the
רשב"ם, the גמרא is making a pretty trivial point that this is
just normal דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. Right. So the question is like
what else would it have been? So the רשב"ם says well, you
know, some think it's just fact finding but at the end of
the day according to the רשב"ם it's not saying anything more than
it's a simple דיני ממונות dinei mammonos case. Okay. And my point
was was that תוספות wants to say no no no, it's saying
more than that, it's saying that the בית דין Beis Din can
impose it if the בית דין Beis Din was there. But for
the רשב"ם *Rashbam* it's just making the simple point that it's a
simple דיני ממונות *dinei mamonos* case. Okay, but תוספות *Tosfos* still allows
us to go into the night as far as I understand? Yes,
he wouldn't disagree with that. He wouldn't disagree with that. He's just
saying it's not the reason for it. Okay, but I want to
go to the next line. The גמרא *Gemara* says ואם היו עסוקין
באותו ענין *v'im hayu asukin b'oso inyan*, if they were occupied with
that case, מותר *mutar*, that they're allowed to finish it at night.
So the גמרא *Gemara* asks מנא הני מילי *mana hanei mili*? What's
the source for this? And the גמרא *Gemara* answers אמר רב חסדא
*amar Rav Chisda*, as it says in the פסוק *pasuk*, ושפטו את
העם בכל עת *v'shaftu es ha'am bechol eis*. They shall judge the
people at all times. If it's all times, it can be at
night.